<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--<!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.dtd">-->
<metadata xml:lang="en"><Esri><MetaID>{376AE373-5B75-430B-9E83-F19535851CE7}</MetaID><CreaDate>20071030</CreaDate><CreaTime>08161800</CreaTime><SyncOnce>FALSE</SyncOnce><SyncDate>20071030</SyncDate><SyncTime>08161900</SyncTime><ModDate>20071030</ModDate><ModTime>08203500</ModTime></Esri><idinfo><descript><langdata Sync="TRUE">en</langdata><purpose>In order to go online to provide the US with complete, current and consistent public domain information on its land use land cover.</purpose></descript><citation><citeinfo><origin>USDA NRCS - National Cartography &amp; Geospatial Center</origin><title>nlcd_az_utm12.tif</title><ftname Sync="TRUE">nlcd_az_utm12.tif</ftname><geoform Sync="TRUE">remote-sensing image</geoform><pubinfo><publish>USDA NRCS - National Cartography &amp; Geospatial Center</publish></pubinfo></citeinfo></citation><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>2007</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress></status><spdom><bounding><westbc Sync="TRUE">-115.941271</westbc><eastbc Sync="TRUE">-107.915214</eastbc><northbc Sync="TRUE">37.652945</northbc><southbc Sync="TRUE">30.533395</southbc></bounding><lboundng><leftbc Sync="TRUE">63388.344800</leftbc><rightbc Sync="TRUE">772288.344800</rightbc><bottombc Sync="TRUE">3386709.680000</bottombc><topbc Sync="TRUE">4167309.680000</topbc></lboundng></spdom><keywords><theme><themekey>imageryBaseMapsEarthCover</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Arizona</placekey></place></keywords><useconst>The U.S. Department of Agriculture, Service Center Agencies should be acknowledged as the data source in products derived from these data. This data set is not designed for use as a primary regulatory tool in permitting or citing decisions, but may be used as a reference source. This is public information and may be interpreted by organizations, agencies, units of government, or others based on needs; however, they are responsible for the appropriate application.  Federal, State, or local regulatory bodies are not to reassign to the Service Center Agencies any authority for the decisions that they make.  The Service Center Agencies will not perform any evaluations of these data for purposes related solely to State or local regulatory programs. Photographic or digital enlargement of these data to scales greater than at which they were originally mapped can cause misinterpretation of the data.  Digital data files are periodically updated, and users are responsible for obtaining the latest version of the data.</useconst><natvform Sync="TRUE">Raster Dataset</natvform><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Ken Becker - Team Leader Cartography &amp; Data Services Team
USDA NRCS National Cartography &amp; Geospatial Center</cntorg></cntperp><cntaddr><address>501 W. Felix Street
Building 23</address><city>Fort Worth</city><state>TX</state><postal>76115</postal></cntaddr></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataIdInfo><envirDesc Sync="TRUE">Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 2; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.2.2.1350</envirDesc><dataLang><languageCode Sync="TRUE" value="en"></languageCode></dataLang><idCitation><resTitle Sync="TRUE">nlcd_az_utm12.tif</resTitle><presForm><PresFormCd Sync="TRUE" value="005"></PresFormCd></presForm></idCitation><spatRpType><SpatRepTypCd Sync="TRUE" value="002"></SpatRepTypCd></spatRpType><dataExt><geoEle><GeoBndBox esriExtentType="native"><westBL Sync="TRUE">63388.3448</westBL><eastBL Sync="TRUE">772288.3448</eastBL><northBL Sync="TRUE">4167309.68</northBL><southBL Sync="TRUE">3386709.68</southBL><exTypeCode Sync="TRUE">1</exTypeCode></GeoBndBox></geoEle></dataExt><geoBox esriExtentType="decdegrees"><westBL Sync="TRUE">-115.941271</westBL><eastBL Sync="TRUE">-107.915214</eastBL><northBL Sync="TRUE">37.652945</northBL><southBL Sync="TRUE">30.533395</southBL><exTypeCode Sync="TRUE">1</exTypeCode></geoBox></dataIdInfo><metainfo><langmeta Sync="TRUE">en</langmeta><metstdn>SCI Minimum Compliance Metadata</metstdn><metstdv>SCI Std 003-02</metstdv><mettc Sync="TRUE">local time</mettc><metc><cntinfo><cntorgp/><cntaddr/></cntinfo></metc><metd>10/30/2007</metd></metainfo><mdLang><languageCode Sync="TRUE" value="en"></languageCode></mdLang><mdStanName Sync="TRUE">ISO 19115 Geographic Information - Metadata</mdStanName><mdStanVer Sync="TRUE">DIS_ESRI1.0</mdStanVer><mdChar><CharSetCd Sync="TRUE" value="004"></CharSetCd></mdChar><mdHrLv><ScopeCd Sync="TRUE" value="005"></ScopeCd></mdHrLv><mdHrLvName Sync="TRUE">dataset</mdHrLvName><distInfo><distributor><distorTran><onLineSrc><linkage Sync="TRUE">file://\\TXFORTWORTD202\C\eo-d-drive\EO_NLCD\nlcdutm\az_04\nlcd_az_utm12.tif</linkage><protocol Sync="TRUE">Local Area Network</protocol><orDesc Sync="TRUE">002</orDesc></onLineSrc><transSize Sync="TRUE">0.000</transSize></distorTran><distorFormat><formatName Sync="TRUE">Raster Dataset</formatName></distorFormat></distributor></distInfo><distinfo><distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Department of Agriculture, no warranty expressed or implied is made by the Service Center Agencies regarding the utility of the data on any other system, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.  The U.S. Department of Agriculture will warrant the delivery of this product in computer readable format, and will offer appropriate adjustment of credit when the product is determined unreadable by correctly adjusted computer input peripherals, or when the physical medium is delivered in damaged condition.  Request for adjustment of credit must be made within 90 days from the date of this shipment from the ordering site. Neither the U.S. Department of Agriculture, nor any of its agencies are liable for misuse of the data, for damage, for transmission of viruses, or for computer contamination through the distribution of these data sets. The U.S. Department of Agriculture prohibits discrimination in all its programs and activities on the basis of race, color, national origin, sex, religion, age, disability, political beliefs, sexual orientation, or marital or family status. (Not all prohibited bases apply to all programs.)</distliab></distinfo><spdoinfo><direct Sync="TRUE">Raster</direct><rastinfo><rasttype Sync="TRUE">Pixel</rasttype><rowcount Sync="TRUE">26020</rowcount><colcount Sync="TRUE">23630</colcount><rastxsz Sync="TRUE">30.000000</rastxsz><rastysz Sync="TRUE">30.000000</rastysz><rastbpp Sync="TRUE">8</rastbpp><vrtcount Sync="TRUE">1</vrtcount><rastorig Sync="TRUE">Upper Left</rastorig><rastcmap Sync="TRUE">FALSE</rastcmap><rastcomp Sync="TRUE">None</rastcomp><rastband Sync="TRUE">1</rastband><rastdtyp Sync="TRUE">pixel codes</rastdtyp><rastplyr Sync="TRUE">FALSE</rastplyr><rastifor Sync="TRUE"></rastifor></rastinfo></spdoinfo><spref><horizsys><cordsysn><geogcsn Sync="TRUE">GCS_North_American_1983</geogcsn><projcsn Sync="TRUE">NAD_1983_UTM_Zone_12N</projcsn></cordsysn><planar><planci><plance Sync="TRUE">row and column</plance><plandu Sync="TRUE">meters</plandu><coordrep><absres Sync="TRUE">30.000000</absres><ordres Sync="TRUE">30.000000</ordres></coordrep></planci><gridsys><gridsysn Sync="TRUE">Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone Sync="TRUE">12</utmzone><transmer><sfctrmer Sync="TRUE">0.999600</sfctrmer><longcm Sync="TRUE">-111.000000</longcm><latprjo Sync="TRUE">0.000000</latprjo><feast Sync="TRUE">500000.000000</feast><fnorth Sync="TRUE">0.000000</fnorth></transmer></utm></gridsys></planar><geodetic><horizdn Sync="TRUE">North American Datum of 1983</horizdn><ellips Sync="TRUE">Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips><semiaxis Sync="TRUE">6378137.000000</semiaxis><denflat Sync="TRUE">298.257222</denflat></geodetic></horizsys></spref><refSysInfo><RefSystem><refSysID><identCode Sync="TRUE">NAD_1983_UTM_Zone_12N</identCode></refSysID></RefSystem></refSysInfo><spatRepInfo><GridSpatRep><numDims Sync="TRUE">2</numDims><cellGeo><CellGeoCd Sync="TRUE" value="002"></CellGeoCd></cellGeo><tranParaAv Sync="TRUE">1</tranParaAv><axDimProps><Dimen><dimName><DimNameTypCd Sync="TRUE" value="002"></DimNameTypCd></dimName><dimSize Sync="TRUE">23630</dimSize><dimResol><value Sync="TRUE">30</value><uom><UomLength><uomName Sync="TRUE">Meter</uomName><conversionToISOstandardUnit Sync="TRUE">1 Meter = 1 Meter(s)</conversionToISOstandardUnit></UomLength></uom></dimResol></Dimen><Dimen><dimName><DimNameTypCd Sync="TRUE" value="001"></DimNameTypCd></dimName><dimSize Sync="TRUE">26020</dimSize><dimResol><value Sync="TRUE">30</value><uom><UomLength><uomName Sync="TRUE">Meter</uomName><conversionToISOstandardUnit Sync="TRUE">1 Meter = 1 Meter(s)</conversionToISOstandardUnit></UomLength></uom></dimResol></Dimen></axDimProps></GridSpatRep></spatRepInfo><eainfo><detailed Name="nlcd_az_utm12.tif.vat"><enttyp><enttypl Sync="TRUE">nlcd_az_utm12.tif.vat</enttypl><enttypt Sync="TRUE">Table</enttypt><enttypc Sync="TRUE">16</enttypc></enttyp><attr><attrlabl Sync="TRUE">OID</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">OID</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">OID</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">4</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale><attrdef Sync="TRUE">Internal feature number.</attrdef><attrdefs Sync="TRUE">ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom Sync="TRUE">Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl Sync="TRUE">VALUE</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">VALUE</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Integer</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">9</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">9</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl Sync="TRUE">COUNT</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">COUNT</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Integer</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">9</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">9</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl Sync="TRUE">Red</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">Red</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">20</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl Sync="TRUE">Green</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">Green</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">20</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl Sync="TRUE">Blue</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">Blue</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">20</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr></detailed><overview><eaover>The state image contains unique color values, for distinctive mapping purposes. 
NLCD 2001 Land Cover Class Definitions 

11. Open Water - All areas of open water, generally with less than 25% cover of vegetation or soil. 

12. Perennial Ice/Snow - All areas characterized by a perennial cover of ice and/or snow, generally greater than 25% of total cover. 

21. Developed, Open Space - Includes areas with a mixture of some constructed materials, but mostly vegetation in the form of lawn grasses. Impervious surfaces account for less than 20 percent of total cover. These areas most commonly include large-lot single-family housing units, parks, golf courses, and vegetation planted in developed settings for recreation, erosion control, or aesthetic purposes 

22. Developed, Low Intensity - Includes areas with a mixture of constructed materials and vegetation. Impervious surfaces account for 20-49 percent of total cover. These areas most commonly include single-family housing units. 

23. Developed, Medium Intensity - Includes areas with a mixture of constructed materials and vegetation. Impervious surfaces account for 50-79 percent of the total cover. These areas most commonly include single-family housing units. 

24. Developed, High Intensity - Includes highly developed areas where people reside or work in high numbers. Examples include apartment complexes, row houses and commercial/industrial. Impervious surfaces account for 80 to100 percent of the total cover. 

31. Barren Land (Rock/Sand/Clay) - Barren areas of bedrock, desert pavement, scarps, talus, slides, volcanic material, glacial debris, sand dunes, strip mines, gravel pits and other accumulations of earthen material. Generally, vegetation accounts for less than 15% of total cover. 

32. Unconsolidated Shore* - Unconsolidated material such as silt, sand, or gravel that is subject to inundation and redistribution due to the action of water. Characterized by substrates lacking vegetation except for pioneering plants that become established during brief periods when growing conditions are favorable. Erosion and deposition by waves and currents produce a number of landforms representing this class. 

41. Deciduous Forest - Areas dominated by trees generally greater than 5 meters tall, and greater than 20% of total vegetation cover. More than 75 percent of the tree species shed foliage simultaneously in response to seasonal change. 

42. Evergreen Forest - Areas dominated by trees generally greater than 5 meters tall, and greater than 20% of total vegetation cover. More than 75 percent of the tree species maintain their leaves all year. Canopy is never without green foliage. 

43. Mixed Forest - Areas dominated by trees generally greater than 5 meters tall, and greater than 20% of total vegetation cover. Neither deciduous nor evergreen species are greater than 75 percent of total tree cover. 

51. Dwarf Scrub - Alaska only areas dominated by shrubs less than 20 centimeters tall with shrub canopy typically greater than 20% of total vegetation. This type is often co-associated with grasses, sedges, herbs, and non-vascular vegetation. 

52. Shrub/Scrub - Areas dominated by shrubs; less than 5 meters tall with shrub canopy typically greater than 20% of total vegetation. This class includes true shrubs, young trees in an early successional stage or trees stunted from environmental conditions. 

71. Grassland/Herbaceous - Areas dominated by grammanoid or herbaceous vegetation, generally greater than 80% of total vegetation. These areas are not subject to intensive management such as tilling, but can be utilized for grazing. 

72. Sedge/Herbaceous - Alaska only areas dominated by sedges and forbs, generally greater than 80% of total vegetation. This type can occur with significant other grasses or other grass like plants, and includes sedge tundra, and sedge tussock tundra. 

73. Lichens - Alaska only areas dominated by fruticose or foliose lichens generally greater than 80% of total vegetation. 

74. Moss - Alaska only areas dominated by mosses, generally greater than 80% of total vegetation. 

81. Pasture/Hay - Areas of grasses, legumes, or grass-legume mixtures planted for livestock grazing or the production of seed or hay crops, typically on a perennial cycle. Pasture/hay vegetation accounts for greater than 20 percent of total vegetation. 

82. Cultivated Crops - Areas used for the production of annual crops, such as corn, soybeans, vegetables, tobacco, and cotton, and also perennial woody crops such as orchards and vineyards. Crop vegetation accounts for greater than 20 percent of total vegetation. This class also includes all land being actively tilled. 

90. Woody Wetlands - Areas where forest or shrubland vegetation accounts for greater than 20 percent of vegetative cover and the soil or substrate is periodically saturated with or covered with water. 

91. Palustrine Forested Wetland* -Includes all tidal and non-tidal wetlands dominated by woody vegetation greater than or equal to 5 meters in height and all such wetlands that occur in tidal areas in which salinity due to ocean-derived salts is below 0.5 percent. Total vegetation coverage is greater than 20 percent. 

92. Palustrine Scrub/Shrub Wetland* - Includes all tidal and non-tidal wetlands dominated by woody vegetation less than 5 meters in height, and all such wetlands that occur in tidal areas in which salinity due to ocean-derived salts is below 0.5 percent. Total vegetation coverage is greater than 20 percent. The species present could be true shrubs, young trees and shrubs or trees that are small or stunted due to environmental conditions. 

93. Estuarine Forested Wetland* - Includes all tidal wetlands dominated by woody vegetation greater than or equal to 5 meters in height, and all such wetlands that occur in tidal areas in which salinity due to ocean-derived salts is equal to or greater than 0.5 percent. Total vegetation coverage is greater than 20 percent. 

94. Estuarine Scrub/Shrub Wetland* - Includes all tidal wetlands dominated by woody vegetation less than 5 meters in height, and all such wetlands that occur in tidal areas in which salinity due to ocean-derived salts is equal to or greater than 0.5 percent. Total vegetation coverage is greater than 20 percent. 

95. Emergent Herbaceous Wetlands - Areas where perennial herbaceous vegetation accounts for greater than 80 percent of vegetative cover and the soil or substrate is periodically saturated with or covered with water. 

96. Palustrine Emergent Wetland (Persistent)* - Includes all tidal and non-tidal wetlands dominated by persistent emergent vascular plants, emergent mosses or lichens, and all such wetlands that occur in tidal areas in which salinity due to ocean-derived salts is below 0.5 percent. Plants generally remain standing until the next growing season. 

97. Estuarine Emergent Wetland* - Includes all tidal wetlands dominated by erect, rooted, herbaceous hydrophytes (excluding mosses and lichens) and all such wetlands that occur in tidal areas in which salinity due to ocean-derived salts is equal to or greater than 0.5 percent and that are present for most of the growing season in most years. Perennial plants usually dominate these wetlands. 

98. Palustrine Aquatic Bed* - The Palustrine Aquatic Bed class includes tidal and nontidal wetlands and deepwater habitats in which salinity due to ocean-derived salts is below 0.5 percent and which are dominated by plants that grow and form a continuous cover principally on or at the surface of the water. These include algal mats, detached floating mats, and rooted vascular plant assemblages. 

99. Estuarine Aquatic Bed* - Includes tidal wetlands and deepwater habitats in which salinity due to ocean-derived salts is equal to or greater than 0.5 percent and which are dominated by plants that grow and form a continuous cover principally on or at the surface of the water. These include algal mats, kelp beds, and rooted vascular plant assemblages. 

* Coastal NLCD class only 

</eaover></overview></eainfo><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20071030</mdDateSt><dataqual><lineage><procstep><procdesc>Download NLCD 2001 image files from the MRLC Consortium. Using the Spatial Analyst Tools in ArcToolbox (ESRI Software) the images are extracted by mask. Then using the Data Management Tools a new mosaic raster image is created. Next Red, Green, and Blue fields are added to the raster image. Using a layer file created from one of the original image files, a join operation is made. Following that a calculation is use to populate the image table. Then a world file is created to go along with the .tif image. </procdesc><procdate>10/5/2007</procdate></procstep><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin><pubdate>January 13, 2007</pubdate><title>National Land Cover Database 2001 (NLCD 2001)</title></citeinfo></srccite><srcscale>1:100000</srcscale></srcinfo></lineage></dataqual></metadata>
